http://www.americanbenefitscouncil.org/our-issues/health/health-information-technology-hipaa-privacy/

HealthRetirementOther Issues
Our Issues
Health
: Health Information Technology & HIPAA Privacy
The Health Insurance Portability and Accountability Act of 1996 (HIPAA) governs the security and privacy of "protected health information" (PHI). This section addresses matters related to such data, including applicability to the Health Information Technology for Economic and Clinical Health Act of 2009 (HITECH).
Legislative	   |
Regulatory		   |
Judicial		   |
Webinars		   |
News Releases
LEGISLATIVE
Source Documents
Bill to Require the Secretary of Health and Human Services to Provide for Recommendations for the Development and Use of Clinical Data Registries for the Improvement of Patient Care (H.R. 5214)
Monday,
July 28,
2014
House Energy and Commerce Committee Draft Legislation Providing for Recommendations on the Development and Use of Clinical Data Registries
Monday,
July 28,
2014
Education and Labor Committee Health Information Technology Amendment to H.R. 3200
Friday,
July 17,
2009
( 15 )
More
Wired for Health Care Quality Act (S. 1693), Senate Floor Version
Thursday,
July
31,
2008
The Protecting Records, Optimizing Treatment and Easing Communication Through Healthcare Technology (PRO(TECH)T) Act (H.R. 6357)(Manager's Amendment)
Tuesday,
July
22,
2008
Topline Changes to the Protecting Records, Optimizing Treatment and Easing Communication Through Healthcare Technology (PRO(TECH)T) Act (H.R. 6357)(Manager's Amendment)
Tuesday,
July
22,
2008
Patient-Controlled Health IT Act (H.R. 6345/Boustany)
Tuesday,
July
1,
2008
Section-by-Section Summary of the PRO(TECH)T Act (Dingell/Barton)
Tuesday,
June
24,
2008
The Protecting Records, Optimizing Treatment and Easing Communication Through Healthcare Technology (PRO(TECH)T) Act (Dingell/Barton)
Tuesday,
June
24,
2008
Promoting Health Information Technology Act (H.R. 6179)(Camp)
Wednesday,
June
4,
2008
Technologies for Restoring Users' Security and Trust (TRUST) in Health Information Act of 2008 (H.R. 5442)(Markey)
Thursday,
February
14,
2008
Privacy in Labor/HHS/Ed Appropriations report (H.R. 3043) as Passed by House and Senate
Thursday,
November
15,
2007
Promoting Health Information Technology Act (H.R. 3800)
Wednesday,
October
10,
2007
Wired for Health Care Quality Act (S. 1693), As Reported by Senate HELP Committee
Wednesday,
August
1,
2007
Health Information Privacy and Security Act (S. 1814)
Wednesday,
July
18,
2007
Privacy in Labor/HHS/Ed Appropriations report (S. 1710)
Wednesday,
June
27,
2007
HHS Secretary Mike Leavitt's Remarks to the National Governors Association on Health Care Transparency
Sunday,
August
6,
2006
Question and Answer Session with HHS Secretary Mike Leavitt at the National Governors Association Meeting on Health Care Transparency
Sunday,
August
6,
2006
Council Materials
Stabilizing Employee Benefit Programs Will Help Get America 'Back to Business'
Tuesday,
August 4,
2020
News Release
'American Benefits Legacy' unveiled: Council report details immense value of employer-provided health, retirement benefits
Wednesday,
October 17,
2018
Correspondence
National Coalition on Benefits Letter to House Leadership on Save American Workers Act (H.R. 3798)
Tuesday,
September 11,
2018
( 14 )
More
Benefits Byte
Council Outlines Health Care Reform Priorities in Letter to Senate Finance Committee Chairman
Thursday,
May
25,
2017
News Release
Employer-sponsored insurance represents strong foundation of American health coverage
Wednesday,
May
24,
2017
News Release
Council urges adoption of a new regulatory framework enabling employers to use technology
Thursday,
May
18,
2017
Memo to Members
Council President's Memo to Members: Policy Priorities Will Need to Overcome Partisan Conflict
Thursday,
November
10,
2016
Research & Policy Reports
A 2020 Vision: Flexibility and the Future of Employee Benefits
Tuesday,
September
23,
2014
Timeline of HIPAA Privacy and Security Provisions (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Friday,
March
6,
2009
Chart of Health IT Provisions in Stimulus Legislation (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Wednesday,
February
18,
2009
Chart of Privacy/HIPAA Provisions in Stimulus Legislation (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Wednesday,
February
18,
2009
Summary of Health IT, Privacy and HIPAA Provisions in Stimulus Legislation (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Wednesday,
February
18,
2009
Group Letter to Senate HELP Committee Regarding Health IT Legislation
Monday,
December
10,
2007
Group Letter to Congress Regarding Health IT Legislation
Wednesday,
June
20,
2007
Group Letter to House of Representatives on Health Information Technology Legislation
Wednesday,
June
14,
2006
Group Letter to House Appropriations on Health Information Technology
Monday,
June
12,
2006
Research & Policy Reports
Safe and Sound: A Ten-Year Plan for Promoting Personal Financial Security
Wednesday,
June
9,
2004
Back to top
REGULATORY
Source Documents
Regulation/Guidance
HHS/CMS Final Regulations on Health IT, Interoperability and Price Transparency
Monday,
March 9,
2020
Regulation/Guidance
HHS/ONC Proposed Regulations on Interoperability, Information Blocking, and the ONC Health IT Certification Program
Monday,
March 4,
2019
Regulation/Guidance
CMS Health Plan Identifier NPRM FAQs
Friday,
December 21,
2018
( 27 )
More
Regulation/Guidance
Request for Information on Modifying HIPAA Rules to Improve Coordinated Care
Friday,
December
14,
2018
Regulation/Guidance
EEOC Final Regulations Regarding Wellness Programs and GINA
Tuesday,
May
17,
2016
Regulation/Guidance
EEOC Final Regulations Regarding Wellness Programs and the ADA
Tuesday,
May
17,
2016
HHS/CMS Request for Information Regarding HPID Requirements
Friday,
May
29,
2015
HHS Shared Nationwide Interoperability Draft Roadmap
Friday,
January
30,
2015
HHS/CMS Delay of Enforcement of HPID Requirement
Friday,
October
31,
2014
HPID Quick Reference Guide from CMS
Friday,
October
10,
2014
Health Insurance Oversight System (HIOS) Health Plan and Other Entity Enumeration System User Manual Version 06.01.00 from CMS
Tuesday,
September
30,
2014
HHS/CMS Frequently Asked Questions on HPID Issues
Monday,
September
29,
2014
Health Plan Identifier (HPID) User Guide from CMS
Wednesday,
September
24,
2014
HHS/CMS Proposed Regulations Regarding Certification of Compliance for Health Plans
Thursday,
January
2,
2014
Proposed Regulations Regarding 90-Day Waiting Period Limitation and Technical Amendments to Certain Health Coverage Requirements Under PPACA
Monday,
March
18,
2013
HHS Final Regulations Modifying the HIPAA Privacy, Security, Enforcement, and Breach Notification Rules under the HITECH Act and GINA; Other Modifications to the HIPAA Rules
Friday,
January
18,
2013
HHS/CMS Proposed Regulations on the Electronic Health Record Incentive Program, Stage 2
Wednesday,
March
7,
2012
HHS Proposed Regulations Regarding HIPAA Privacy Rule under HITECH Act
Tuesday,
May
31,
2011
HHS/CMS Final Regulations on the Electronic Health Record Incentive Program
Wednesday,
July
28,
2010
HHS/ONC Final Regulations on Health Information Technology Standards
Wednesday,
July
28,
2010
HHS Proposed Regulations for Modifications to the HIPAA Privacy, Security, and Enforcement Rules under the HITECH Act
Wednesday,
July
14,
2010
FTC Final Regulations on Protected Health Information, as Published in Federal Register
Tuesday,
August
25,
2009
HHS Final Regulations on Protected Health Information, as Published in Federal Register
Monday,
August
24,
2009
FTC Final Regulations on Protected Health Information
Wednesday,
August
19,
2009
FTC Protected Health Information Breach Notification Form
Wednesday,
August
19,
2009
HHS Final Regulations on Protected Health Information
Wednesday,
August
19,
2009
HHS Guidance and Request for Information Regarding Protected Health Information
Monday,
April
27,
2009
FTC Guidance and Request for Information Regarding Protected Health Information
Monday,
April
20,
2009
Tri-agency RFI on Benefit-Specific Waiting Periods Under HIPAA Titles I & IV
Thursday,
December
30,
2004
Treasury/DOL/HHS Interim Final Rules for Nondiscrimination in Health Coverage in the Group Market
Monday,
January
8,
2001
Council Materials
Comment Letter
Council Letter to HHS/ONC Regarding Proposed Regulations on Interoperability, Information Blocking and ONC Health IT Certification Program
Monday,
June 3,
2019
Comment Letter
Council Letter to CMS on Rescinding the Adoption of the Health Plan Identifier (HPID)
Tuesday,
February 19,
2019
News Release
'American Benefits Legacy' unveiled: Council report details immense value of employer-provided health, retirement benefits
Wednesday,
October 17,
2018
( 22 )
More
News Release
Council urges adoption of a new regulatory framework enabling employers to use technology
Thursday,
May
18,
2017
Council Summary
Highlights from the Obama Administration’s October 2015 Regulatory Agendas and IRS Priority Guidance Plan
Friday,
December
18,
2015
Comment Letter
Council Letter to CMS on Request for Information Regarding HPID Requirements
Tuesday,
July
28,
2015
Consumer-Purchase Alliance, Council Group Letter to HHS Regarding the Draft Shared Nationwide Interoperability Roadmap
Friday,
April
3,
2015
Comment Letter
Council Comments to CMS on Proposed Regulations Regarding Certification of Compliance for Health Plans
Tuesday,
April
1,
2014
P4P Presentation Slides:
Friday,
February
21,
2014
P4P Presentation Slides: New ACA Mandate: HIPAA Health Plan Certification Proposed Rules (Christy Tinnes, Groom Law Group)
Friday,
February
21,
2014
Summary of New HIPAA Certification Requirement (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Tuesday,
February
4,
2014
Consumer-Purchaser Disclosure Project Letter to CMS Regarding Health IT Meaningful Use Program
Monday,
May
7,
2012
Council/Chamber Comment Letter to HHS Regarding HITECH and HIPAA Privacy Rules
Monday,
August
1,
2011
Summary of HITECH Regulations for HIPAA Accounting of Disclosures (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Wednesday,
July
13,
2011
Consumer-Purchaser Disclosure Project Comments to Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology on 2012 Physician Quality Reporting System
Friday,
February
25,
2011
Consumer-Purchaser Disclosure Project Comments to Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology on Meaningful Use Stage 2
Friday,
February
25,
2011
Confidentiality Coalition Comments to HHS on Proposed HITECH Modifications to the HIPAA Privacy, Security and Enforcement Rules
Monday,
September
13,
2010
Group Letter to HHS in Support of Health Information Technology and Quality Initiatives
Thursday,
August
5,
2010
Council Comments to HHS on the Interim Final Rule for Breach Notification for Unsecured Protected Health Information
Friday,
October
23,
2009
Summary of Final Regulations on Protected Health Information (Courtesy of Groom Law Group)
Tuesday,
August
25,
2009
Council Comment Letter to FTC Regarding Protected Health Information Guidance
Monday,
June
1,
2009
Council Comment Letter to HHS on Guidance and Request for Information Regarding Protected Health Information
Thursday,
May
21,
2009
Groom Law Group Chart: HITECH Act (H.R. 1) Timeline of HIPAA Privacy & Security Provisions
Monday,
May
11,
2009
Groom Law Group Chart: Security Breach Notification Requirement
Monday,
May
11,
2009
Groom Law Group Memo: HHS Guidance on Protected Health Information
Monday,
May
11,
'American Benefits Legacy' unveiled: Council report details immense value of employer-provided health, retirement benefits
Wednesday,
October 17,
2018
Employer-sponsored insurance represents strong foundation of American health coverage
Wednesday,
May 24,
2017
Council urges adoption of a new regulatory framework enabling employers to use technology
Thursday,
May 18,
2017
( 1 )
More
American Benefits Council sets course for Year 2020 with strategic plan for health, retirement policy
Tuesday,
September
23,
2014
